Roger Stern papers, circa 1955-1978
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Roger Stern Papers, circa 1955-1978
MS 304
Stern, Roger, 1915-
Contains biographical information, subject files, reports and printed materials, 1955-1978, relating chiefly to his career as an engineer and manager at Compañia Minera de Cananea in Sonora, Mexico, and as a consultant with the firm Pincock, Allen and Holt in Tucson, Arizona.
1.75 feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Roger Stern was born September 17, 1915 in New York, New York and raised in California. He attended schools in Glendale and graduated from San Diego State University in 1938 with a B.S. in Physics. He served in the U.S. Navy in the field of Aviation Electronics from December 1944 to March 1946. Roger Stern married Caroline Vota Stern; they had 3 children.
His extensive career in the mineral industry spanned more than 40 years; he worked mainly in Mexico. From 1937 to 1941, he began as an assayer-metallurgist and superintendent at the El Fenomeno Mine in Ensenada, Baja California. From 1941 until 1955, Stern worked for American Smelting and Refining Company (ASARCO) in various lead-zinc operations in Mexico, including positions in ore testing, metallurgical accounting, and management.
In 1955, Stern resigned from ASARCO to accept the position of Chief Metallurgist with Cananea Consolidated Copper Company in Sonora, Mexico, also known as Compañia Minera de Cananea. During his twenty-two years with the company, he held various positions, and retired on September 30, 1977, as Assistant General Manager. Following his retirement, Stern acted as a consultant for Pincock, Allen and Holt, a mining industry consulting company in Tucson, Arizona. His expertise was in the fields of mineral dressing, flotation, crushing, copper smelting, and fire refining.
Scope and Content Note
Contains biographical information, subject files, reports and printed materials, 1955-1978, relating chiefly to his career as an engineer and manager at Compañia Minera de Cananea in Sonora, Mexico, and as a consultant with the firm Pincock, Allen and Holt in Tucson, Arizona.
The majority of the alphabetically arranged files reflect topics concerning copper mining operations in Cananea, Mexico. Each file may contain correspondence, memorandum, research notes, blueprints, or printed materials from administrators, researchers, or suppliers to Stern relating to various processes and products in the mine. The major departments of the mine were Open Pit Mining, Concentrator, Leaching and Precipitation, and Smelting; support facilities included power genera-tion, shops, and railroad.
The largest files are: Cananea Reports, which contain documents on particular phases of the operation; Field Trips and Other Operations, which were written by Stern and other engineers in the 1950s and 1960s and detail visits or studies of related mining ventures, mainly in Arizona; Pincock, Allen & Holt, which contain his consulting activities during the late 1970s; and Supplementary Printed Materials, which hold brochures, equipment catalogs, and similar information on a wide variety of mining topics. Of interest in this folder is his copy of Contrato Colectivo y Reglamento Interior de Trabajo (Cananea, 1975) concerning labor and management relations at the mine.
Some materials in Spanish.
Access Terms
Stern, Roger, 1915 -- Archives
Cananea Consolidated Copper Co.
Copper mines and mining -- Mexico -- Cananea
Mines and mineral resources -- Mexico -- Sonora (State)
Mining engineers -- Archives
Industries -- Mexico -- Cananea
Reports
Correspondence
Container List
- Biographical Information. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Bagdad Mine Report. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Cananea Reports. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
- Cement Cu Blocks. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Cement Cu Smeltering. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chemical Smeltering. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Converter Slag. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Concentrate Drying. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Cyanidation. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Cyclones. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Field Trips and Other Operations. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
- Flash Smelter. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Flotations. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Fluo Solids. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Fuel and Combustion. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- IMIQ Convention: Quimieros Instituto Mexico de Ingenieros. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Instrumentation: Rillito. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Intermediate Products. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Kennecott Ray Meeting. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Leaching. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Lime Plant. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Metallurgy Notes. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Mining Congress. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Phosphate. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Pincock, Allen & Holt, Inc. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Pit Organization. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Plants. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Relocation Filler Plant. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Relocation Filler Plant. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Retirement Information. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Roast Leach Electrowinning. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Soft Rubber Lined Pumps. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Seminar: Organization and Operation of a Modern Maintenance Program (Atlanta, Georgia: 1977). 1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Slag. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Smelter Byproduct Treatment. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Smelter Casting Machine. circa 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Smelting. circa 1955-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Smelting: Metallurgy. circa 1955-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Soil Conditioner. circa 1955-1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Solvent Extraction. circa 1955-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Storage Piles. circa 1955-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sulfuric Acid. circa 1955-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Supplementary Printed Materials. circa 1955-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Tailings. circa 1955-1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)